[Music]
the public health community appears to
have all but given up on eliminating
obesity
the latest world health organization
goals include a 2025 obesity target of
just trying to shoot for no further
increase
even such a modest sounding low bar may
represent one of the greatest challenges
facing global health one in which we are
failing
though there has been isolated pockets
of patchy progress no country has yet
reversed the epidemic
blame has been laid at the feet of the
food industry lobby
the promotion of the over consumption of
high calorie low nutrient foods and
beverages has been identified as the
major driver of the obesity pandemic
now that we have rid much of the world
of pestilence and famines some public
health proponents have gone as far as to
suggest that the new vectors of disease
are taking the form of transnational
food corporations that market salt fat
sugar and calories in unprecedented
quantities
it's considered the world's biggest
industry the processed food makers may
alone bring in trillions
put simply concluded a senior director
at a global health institute the
enormous commercial success enjoyed by
the food industry is now causing what
promises to be one of the greatest
public health disasters of our time
but it's not their fault corporations
just do what they're set up to do their
goal is not to make people fat just to
make people money
the food industry manipulates
ingredients such as salt sugar and fat
and spikes in caffeine and flavor
enhancing chemicals for reasons no more
nefarious than maximizing profits it's
just to exploit our natural biological
vulnerabilities markets often
incentivize companies to cater to and
take advantage of human weaknesses the
food and beverage ceos are not out doing
victory laps in children's hospital
halls to revel in their handiwork they
may simply have a fiduciary
responsibility to maximize quarterly
profits for their shareholders it's just
how the system works
but why do the corporations sell apple
jacks instead of apples or orange crush
instead of oranges
to quote from the apocryphal slick willy
sutton answer on why he robbed banks
that's where the money is
the reason some of the unhealthiest
foods are marketed is one of simple
economics real food goes bad
fruits and vegetables are perishable
what shareholders want is a snack cake
that lasts for weeks on the shelves
real food doesn't have brand names why
would even a broccoli grower put an ad
on tv for broccoli when you'd likely
just buy their competitors broccoli
the system is just not set up to reward
the sale of health promoting food what
kind of profit margins can you get on a
sweet potato
real food costs money to grow
shareholders don't want dirt they want
dirt cheap commodities discounted by
taxpayer subsidies they can mix with
carbonated water and sell for a few
bucks a bottle
dollar menu burgers are thanks in part
to hundreds of billions of dollars of
federal subsidies for cheap feed those
who resist calls for heavy-handed
government regulation may not realize
those heavy hands are already pressing
down the scale on the side of big
business even without regulations the
market can be rapidly responsive but
only within certain parameters the
gluten-free craze is a great example how
many people had even heard of the word
10 years ago and now some surveys
suggest as much as 30 percent of the
population is trying to avoid it this
led to a 10 000 plus explosion in
products labeled gluten-free including
from major players such as tyson foods
launching gluten-free bacon and lunch
meat
ironically gluten-free products may be
less healthy with more sugar and salt
less fiber
but are mostly just different shades of
the same processed junk a gluten-free
doughnut is still a doughnut a
nutritional analysis of foods marketed
to children found that about 90 percent
of products both gluten free and not
were classified as
unhealthy
that's the limit of the market
the invisible hand is more than happy to
hand us any kind of junk we want low-fat
junk low-carb junk non-gmo organic junk
and especially ironic processed paleo
junk
they can make money off of any fad
except
food
shareholders can profit off any kind of
funyuns but can't do much with real
onions
within a narrow scope of commodity
components and chemicals endless
reformulations can fit any fashionable
flavor of the month but produce will
never be as profitable the market even
prevents food manufacturers from taking
small steps to make their products less
detrimental such as lowering salt or
sugar content any deviation from the
levels perfectly engineered for maximum
cravability will get you immediately
undercut by your competitors
how then was england able to so
successfully lower sodium intakes
associated with a dramatic drop in
stroke and heart disease deaths
because they did it across the board
mcdonald's chicken mcnuggets have two
and a half times more salt in the u.s
than the uk but that's because burger
king was cutting down too
in the best documented population level
sodium reduction to date the british
government formed public-private
partnerships with major food
manufacturers retailers and restaurant
chains to simultaneously reduce sodium
levels so slowly over the years no one
would notice
the secret sauce may have been the level
playing field so no company could gain a
commercial advantage by out-salting
competitors
analogous proposals have called for the
stepwise gradual unobtrusive reduction
in sugar and soft drinks to affect a
similar shift in taste preferences on a
population-wide scale
this all sounds a bit big brothery
realize that people can still season and
sweeten to their heart's desire or
rather detriment
you can salt your nuggets all you want
dump the whole shaker on
chug a bottle of corn syrup it's all
still your body your choice
it's like the proposed cap on soft drink
sizes you can still drink all the soda
you want it's trying to make the default
options a little healthier it's easier
to add salt to food on your plate than
it is to remove it
the life-saving success of the trans fat
ban and society-wide sodium reduction
may lie in the convenience of improving
consumers diets without them having to
change their behaviors
some view this as government overreach
but the slipperiest slope may be that of
inaction as the director of yale center
for food policy and obesity as pointed
out governments initially defaulted to
business interests in the case of
tobacco to try to counter all the
industry lies with weak and ineffective
attempts at consumer education and look
what happened the unnecessary deaths
could be counted
in the millions
the u.s can ill afford to repeat this
mistake with diet
until the political will is summoned to
make industry-wide changes in our food
supply we need to take personal
responsibility for our own health for
our family's health
because it may be a matter
of life and death so
what does that personal solution look
like in the interim that's exactly why i
wrote how not to diet
check it out at your local public
library
[Music]
so
you